CLAIRE M REMINGTON

303-1519 Hillside Ave, Victoria, BC, Canada • 778-535-4249 claireremington@gmail.com • www.claireremington.com

PROFESSIONAL PPROFILE

An interdisciplinary researcher and analyst with a decade of experience focused on improving communities' sustainability and resilience. My strengths include project management, stakeholder consultation, and technical communication. I have also taught university-level civil engineering courses with a focus on sustainable natural resource management and public health engineering in low-resource contexts.

EDUCATION

MASc Civil Engineering

Victoria, BC, Canada

University of Victoria

Dec 2019

Public Health & Environmental Engineering Lab

Relevant coursework: Industrial Metabolism and Global Environmental Change; Urban Metabolism and Sustainable Cities; Water and Sanitation Engineering for Developing Countries; and Design and Analysis of Experiments.

BA Chemistry Portland, OR, USA

Reed College May 2011

Relevant coursework: Environmental Chemistry; International Environmental Politics; Ecological Literature; and Natural Resource Economics.

IB Bilingual (French) Diploma

Nairobi, Kenya

International School of Kenya

June 2007

RELEVANT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Sustainable Organic Integrated Livelihoods (SOIL)

Remote (Victoria, BC)

Sanitation Planning Analyst

Aug 2020-Present

Developing financial projections and a terms of reference for a Payment-by-Results contract funded by the Inter-American Development Bank (IDB) and arranged between DINEPA (the Haitian ministry for water and sanitation) and SOIL as the sanitation service provider.

Public Health & Environmental Engineering Services Contractor July 2019-Present

Key Project: Community Composting Toilet

Fundraised for and designed a composting toilet for installation at the University of Victoria Campus Community Garden. Collaborated with stakeholders from the University of Victoria (including the Office of Campus Planning and Sustainability as well as Facilities Management), Lintott Architecture, and the lead author and editors of the BC Ministry of Health's Manual of Composting Toilets and Greywater Practice.

Feasibility Study: Composting Toilet Residuals Processing Facility for Hornby Island

Supported the CVRD-funded evaluation of the feasibility of installing a composting toilet residuals processing facility on Hornby Island. Provided technical and regulatory support for the technical analysis and business case for a residuals processing facility. Co-wrote articles and FAQs to promote interest in the community-wide survey and responded to public enquiries.

Grant Application: Biosolids Engineering Research

Managed grant application for research funding to perform an options analysis for the long-term use of

biosolids in Capital Regional District. Led proposal development meetings and collaborated with stakeholders from the WSÁNEĆ Leadership Council, Gwaii Engineering, and the Public Health & Environmental Engineering Lab at the University of Victoria.

Ultimate Spirit

Vancouver Island, BC, Canada

Ultimate Frishee Coach

April 2019-Present

- Coach Ultimate Frisbee to youths aged 6-18 years old in Indigenous communities and schools on Vancouver Island in collaboration with the Indigenous Sport, Physical Activity, and Recreation Council (ISPARC).
- Co-wrote a successful application for CAD 180,000 from Sport for Social Development in Indigenous Communities (SSDIC) funded by the Government of Canada.
- Co-develop a curriculum guideline for the delivery of Ultimate Frisbee-related outreach programs to Indigenous communities.

University of Victoria

Victoria, BC, Canada

Sessional Instructor

Jan 2020-August 2020

- Created and delivered technical content for two 4th year civil engineering courses: 1) Water and Sanitation for Developing Countries, and 2) Solid Waste, Air, and Water Pollution.
- Supervised, trained, and mentored 3 teaching assistants so that they had the methods and confidence to fulfill their responsibilities; this included working with them to self-assess performance, collaborating on content development, and sharing constructive feedback.

First Nations Health Authority

Victoria, BC, Canada

Co-op Student, Climate Change & Health

Jan 2020-May 2020

- Developed CCHAP (Climate Change & Health Adaptation Program) funding application materials including a program overview document, an application and budget template, and a process to evaluate CCHAP applications.
- Supported the development of a project evaluation process.

University of Victoria

Victoria, BC, Canada

Master's Thesis Research

Ian 2018-Dec 2019

- Evaluated the design of sustainable sanitation systems from different but complementary perspectives:

 1) an examination of impact of sanitation on the global nitrogen cycle via material flow analysis; 2) a derivation of fundamental drying characteristics of fresh faeces via lab-based environmental engineering research; and 3) a qualitative assessment of the readiness of the regulatory environment, technology, and adopters for an alternative (composting toilet) sanitation system.
- Demonstrated that the design of sustainable sanitation systems is an urgent issue that is both local and global in scale.
- Established that there is work that needs to be done to innovate the technology available, promote an enabling environment, and challenge society regarding its assumptions around what is acceptable when it comes to the choice and accessibility of sanitation systems.

Sustainable Organic Integrated Livelihoods (SOIL)

Cap-Haitien, Haiti

Sanitation Planning Analyst

Jan 2015-Dec 2017

- Supervised consultant teams and research initiatives focused on improving the occupational health and safety, process economics, and public health risk associated with SOIL's household and commercial sanitation services.
- Co-created annual strategy development and budgeting for SOIL's USD 500,000 household sanitation program and the USD 100,000 commercial sanitation program.
- Led the Sanitation Safety Planning working group and liaised with non-governmental organizations,

community associations, residents, and representatives from the Haitian government ministries of the environment, agriculture, and public health.

Blue Hill Partners

Philadelphia, PA, USA

Project Development Analyst

Iun 2013-Dec 2015

- Collaborated with the Pennsylvania Treasury Department to lead the investment of over USD 45 million in energy efficiency, climate change mitigation, and sustainability projects at Pennsylvania colleges and universities.
- Conducted cost-benefit analyses and developed financial models to analyze investment risks and potential emissions savings associated with clean technology retrofits.
- Managed the process of certifying the firm as a B Corp.
- Supervised 2 research assistants.

Let Us Compost

Athens, GA, USA

Pick-Up Expert

Sept 2012-Jan 2013

- Played an integral role in the operations and start-up of a curbside food scrap pickup and composting service to sustainably manage organic waste streams.
- Collected and transported organic waste streams for composting.

Sustainable Northwest

Portland, OR, USA

Thermal Energy Analyst

Aug 2011-Mar 2012

 Collaborated with the Oregon Department of Energy to investigate Oregon's thermal energy baseline, summarize information about communities and Oregonians not served by natural gas utilities, and profile industrial process heat use.

LEADERSHIP

Victoria Ultimate Player Society (VUPS) Board Member and Treasurer	June 2019-Present
University of Victoria Campus Community Garden Board Member	Apr 2019-Present
University of Victoria Vixens' Ultimate Frisbee Coach	Sept 2020-Present
Gulls 'n' Buoys Mixed Ultimate Frisbee Captain	Apr 2019-Aug 2019
Reed College Women's Ultimate Frisbee Captain	Aug 2008-May 2011

PUBLICATIONS

Remington, C., Kennedy, C., Whittredge, P., & Dorea, C. (2020). The Potential Impact of Ecological Sanitation on the Nitrogen Cycle, (under review at PLOS ONE).

Remington, C., Bourgault, C., & Dorea, C. (2019). Measurement and modelling of moisture sorption isotherm and heat of sorption of fresh faeces, *Water* **2020**.

Bourgault, C., Lessard, P., **Remington, C.**, & Dorea, C. (2019). Experimental determination of moisture sorption isotherm of faecal sludge. *Water* 2019.

Remington, C., Jean, L., Kramer, S., Boys, J., & Dorea, C. (2018). Process cost analysis for the optimization of a container-based sanitation service in Haiti. WEDC Conference 2018.

Remington, C., Cherrak, M., Preneta, N., & Kramer, S. (2016). A social business model for the provision of household ecological sanitation services in urban Haiti. WEDC 41st International Conference, 1–6.

Remington, C., Davis, C., and Krumenauer, M. (2012). Oregon's Thermal Energy Baseline, (August).

Remington, C. (2011) Some Concrete Chemistry: The Effect of Sound Walls on Benzene Concentration (Bachelor's Thesis, Reed College, Portland, Oregon).

N. Netusil, **C. Remington** et al. (2009) Valuing the Benefits of Ecosystem Services Generated by the Reed College Canyon Restoration Project: 1999-2009 (project paper for Econ 352, Reed College, Portland, Oregon).

PRESENTATIONS

Remington, C., Bourgault, C., & Dorea, C. (2019). "Measurement and modelling of moisture sorption isotherm and heat of sorption of fresh faeces." Accepted for poster presentation at UNC Water and Health Conference 2019, Chapel Hill, North Carolina.

Remington, C., Bourgault, C., & Dorea, C. (2019). Moisture sorption characteristics of fresh faeces. Accepted for oral presentation at West 2019 Conference, Vancouver, BC, Canada.

Remington, C. (2019). Implementing composting toilet systems in BC and worldwide. Accepted for oral presentation at BCWWA 2019, Victoria, BC, Canada.

Septien, S., Getahun, S., Mirara, S., Makununika, B.S., Mugauri, T.R., Naidoo, D., Singh, A., Pocock, J., Inambao, F., Onabanjo, T., Winrow, E., Mabbett, I., Sellgren, K.L., Bourgault, C., **Remington, C.**, Dorea, C., & Buckley, C.A. (2019). Investigation of faecal sludge drying from on-site sanitation facilities. Accepted for oral presentation at 10th Asia Pacific Drying Conference, Vadadora, India.

Remington, C., Bourgault, C., & Dorea, C. (2018). Improving understanding of faecal drying for application to a humanitarian emergency toilet design. Accepted for poster presentation at WEDC Conference 2018, Nakuru, Kenya.

Remington, C., Dorea, C., & Bourgault, C. (2018). Improving understanding of faecal sludge drying for application to a humanitarian emergency toilet design. Accepted for oral presentation at WEST 2018 Conference, Vancouver, BC, Canada.

Kramer, S., Lloyd, E., **Remington, C.**, & Preneta, N. (2017). EkoLakay — Developing a Social Business for the Provision of Household Sanitation in Dense Urban Settings. Accepted for oral presentation at 4th International Fecal Sludge Management, Chennai, India.

Preneta, N., Mesa, B., Kramer, S., & **Remington, C.** (2017). Thermophilic composting as an effective waste treatment option in low-resource settings. Accepted for poster presentation at 4th International Fecal Sludge Management, Chennai, India.

Remington, C., Agarwal, R., Kramer S., Mesa B., Buluswar, S., & Preneta, N. (2017). Developing Process Cost Analysis Methodology for Faecal Sludge Management (FSM). Accepted for poster presentation at 4th International Fecal Sludge Management, Chennai, India.